Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So, today's דף daf is... today's דף
daf is קטז, Kuf-Tet-Zayin, 116. And we pick
up four lines from the top, ויאמרו. Vayomeru. There were some questions
yesterday, but let's read a little bit and then I'll go back
and I'll discuss the questions because I actually did find some answers
about them. Anyway, but we're dealing with the basic משנה mishnah that
lays out the order of who gets first and the idea that
you go down in generations to find out if somebody can replace
somebody who's not alive before you go on to the next person
in the chart. We'll review that again. But let's first get into
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so it says like this, quoting a פסוק
pasuk here in
שופטים: Shoftim: ויאמרו ירשת פליטה לבנימן ולא ימחה שבט מישראל. Vayomeru yerushat
pleitah l'Vinyamin v'lo yimacheh shevet miYisrael. So this was after the
פילגש בגבעה, Pilegesh b'Givah, and there was only 600 men left of
בנימין, Binyamin, and the other tribes sort of tried arranged so that
some of their daughters whatever would get taken by the men of
בנימין, Binyamin, so to protect them, make sure that they could repopulate
and the tribe would not be wiped out. This of course also
is echoing the statement on yesterday's דף, daf, which says that we
have a tradition דלא כלה שבטא, d'lo khalah shivta, right, that no
tribe will ever be completely destroyed. So here it almost happened anyway,
and they said, so the question is what do they mean by
a ירושה, yerushah, an inheritance for the remnant of בנימין, Binyamin, and
the tribe will not be wiped out. So what's that word ירושה?
yerushah? Obviously very significant given or suggestive given our context.
So אמר רבי יצחק דבי רבי אמי מלמד שהתנו על שבט בנימין
שלא תירש בת הבן עם האחים, Amar Rabbi Yitzhak d'be Rebi Ammi
melamed she-hitnu al shevet Binyamin she-lo tirash bat haben im ha'ahim, that
a daughter of a son will not get with his brothers. So,
see now, good you told me to take a picture of this
because now I have to erase this. Where's the eraser? Do we
not have an eraser?
I think I know, I think it's in another classroom. Oh really?
I think so.
All righty. So, use my hand anyway.
All right, anyway, we'll start just drawing it over here, okay? Here,
we'll get a, but anyway. All right, so here you go, guy
dies and actually imagine, let's call this guy צלפחד. Tzelofchad. Okay, no,
not צלפחד, Tzelofchad, חפר.
Chefer. Okay, ah, thank you.
Okay, so,
here
we go.
Here's חפר. Chefer. Here's צלפחד. Tzelofchad.
Okay, here's צלפחד's Tzelofchad brothers.
Okay,
this is צלפחד. Tzelofchad. Okay, then צלפחד Tzelofchad has his—anybody know? Pop
quiz! What are the names of בנות צלפחד? Bnot Tzelofchad? What? One
more time.
מחלה, Machlah, נעה, No'ah, חגלה. Hoglah.
Am I spelling it right? Milkah... Here, sorry, I forgot one.
מחלה, Machlah, נעה, No'ah, חגלה, Hoglah, מלכה, Milkah, and תרצה. Tirtzah.
חגלה... Hoglah...
oh, Orpah's Ruth. חגלה, Hoglah, מלכה, Milkah, and תרצה. Tirtzah.
I figured we should have to make like little piles of עצים
etzim by צלפחד. Tzelofchad. Of what? עצים. etzim. Okay, anyway, here they
are.
Okay, anyway.
All right, so. Okay, anyway, so, we said if somebody isn't around,
his children take his place. Now, first of all, here's a חידוש
chiddush that we might not have said. Maybe if he's not around,
maybe his children only take his place
if there's no
surviving... meaning you have three kids, three boys. One is dead. Okay.
So maybe, okay, then it only goes to the two surviving sons.
Right? Maybe you only go down a generation if there's nobody else
at this line. The answer is that that's not true. That even
in the presence of these other brothers, his children, their nieces, their
nephews, or whatever, will take the place of their father. And in
this case, even if they're women, right? So now you're going to
have together with these brothers, these their nieces up here taking the
place of their father. That's the case of בנות צלפחד, Bnot Tzelofchad,
all right? Because the גמרא Gemara says they didn't just inherit צלפחד's
Tzelofchad property, they inherited חפר's Chefer property as well.
We discussed that. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says in the—that's
what one of the things we learned yesterday. In the case of
שבט בנימין, shevet Binyamin, we said—so we're going to ignore this—it won't
be—but it'll be שבט בנימין. shevet Binyamin. They said in a case
like this, and let's just say he's got one—he's got one daughter
or whatever. In a case like this, it will not pass down
to the daughters. Only the brothers will get it. If he had
sons and he wasn't around, it would go to his sons, but
not to his daughters. Why? Because since they only had 600 people
left of the tribe of בנימין, Binyamin, so everybody is getting a
huge portion in... the land of בנימין. Binyamin. If any land at
that stage were to pass on to a woman and then she
would marry out, you would have a major section of the tribe
pass out of the sort of the you know of the property
of בנימין. Binyamin. So, this so anyway this does not prevent it
eventually going to a woman, because you can pass it on to
one of these guys and then he can die and then it
could go to his daughter, right? We're not completely preventing it to
go to a woman, right? But in the case where there are
you know there there are like where we could sort of a
certain limited amount we're not going to have we didn't say it
never goes to a daughter, but if there's sons to give it
to we won't give it to granddaughters even though the granddaughters should
be taking the place of their father. Okay? So that was a
special תקנה takanah they made, you know, not permanently but until enough
the generation could repopulate and then we could allow so this is
obviously sensitive to the idea, right? That when it goes to a
girl it does go out of the tribe. So, a woman. It
goes out of the tribe. So this is sort of saying there
was a time when they wouldn't let that happen. Yes.
It's the reverse of the case we had yesterday about it didn't
go to the sister but it would go to the brother's descendants
even though a girl. Right. The opposite and also it's the same
questioning then it just puts off the transfer.
Right. But they figured they'll do what they'll do the most they
can and they'll put it off for a while until the tribe
can repopulate and then the amount of property that could pass to
a woman at any given time would be a smaller amount. But
again this would only you know this is only so helpful like
you know they could have made it much because it passes on
to his sons and then a son dies and he only has
a daughter. Right? So it doesn't even it's not even that helpful
you know you might have imagined that it would have said that
they would have said that like it never goes to any for
this generation it's always going to go to a male heir and
not a female heir, you know. But they anyway but the גמרא
Gemara makes it more limited. I mean within this statement that that's
what happened. Okay. אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי. Amar
Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai. So said רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan in the name of רבי שמעון בן יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai, כל שאינו מניח בן ליורשו kol she'eino maniach ben leyoresho now
that's a now the sort of the patriarchy is reasserting itself, okay?
Now we've introduced the whole thing about בנות צלפחד Benot Tzelofchad and
you know how girls can get and not only can girls get
even a girl can get together with the guys when she's representing
her father, right? So we've had all of this stuff about how
now
women are part of the I mean I'm whatever I'm only saying
because I'm talking about children but anyway how women but adult children
how women are part of the whole process and that can be
disruptive, right? And now we're sort of like saying oh no but
that's why it's really important to have sons so that you know
to maintain now we would say people say like if somebody dies
and he doesn't leave sons and especially in places where women take
their you know husband's names it's like so like that's the end
of my family name, right? You know my name is no longer
you know and and so there is still some remnant of that
the way people feel today, right? That last name especially you know
who's gonna carry on my last name if I don't if I
don't have any sons? So in the גמרא, Gemara, you know, it
was also about this you know the land as well and the
the you know the maintaining it within as we've seen the patriarchal
home. Alright, so now we're talking about what happens if that's the
case. So כל שאינו מניח בן ליורשו kol she'eino maniach ben leyoresho
anybody that does not leave over a son to inherit him and
presumably meaning that it'll be inherited by a daughter or maybe it
means by I don't know by a brother but it's not considered
a true like a continuation of the person, so הקדוש ברוך הוא
מלא עליו עברה. Hakadosh Baruch Hu maleh alav evrah. God fills is
filled with wrath against this person.
זאב הכא Zeev hakha
I know and the גמרא'ס Gemara's gonna get to the I know
so the גמרא Gemara is gonna get to the issue like about
fault. העברתם את נחלתו. Havartem et nachalato. You shall pass you shall
transfer the נחלה nachala to the daughter, לבתו. levito. So he said
the word there transfer as opposed to give is because it's going
to leave the tribe. But here it's using the word העברתם havartem
as עברה, evrah, you know, wrath. So God is filled with wrath
because it
breaks the sense of the you know it doesn't seem like we're
limiting it to the ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and when it leads
to a you know to a piece of the of the tribal
land going out. It seems like we're more abstracting it. And but
you know that it's then to some degree there's no continuation of
this person. But you're right it's a little bit of a shame
like because I presumably people feel that way as well particularly in
a you know a real you know in those in in a
in a more profoundly patriarchal society and the person I'm sure is
very upset himself so how does it help to say God is
as angry with
him?
Yes. Or is it like meaning do you not have sons because
God is pissed at you or do
you...
you know maybe it's causal the other way. I think the גמרא
Gemara would have said that it would have said like סימן הוא
שהקדוש ברוך הוא siman hu shehakadosh baruch hu or something like that
משום שהקדוש ברוך הוא. mishum shehakadosh baruch hu. But even so that
doesn't also make it great. So great now I don't have a
son and everybody thinks it's because I'm a sinner and God is
angry at me. So it's like...
צדיק ורע
לו Tzadik vera lo right exactly.
So we're going to have a story about this, about actually a
great אמורא amora who did not leave any children behind.
Yes, and there's something in the liturgy in terms of saying קדיש
kaddish as the son.
Oh, the son to say קדיש, kaddish, right. Yeah, but then and
then the whole discussion about a daughter saying קדיש kaddish and the
פוסקים poskim saying that really yes, that a daughter can, the whole
discussion was around whether it was like, you know, appropriate for the
norms or whatever. But anyway, okay.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, יום עברה וצרה ביום
ההוא Yom evrah vetzarah bayom hahu וכתיב על דאמר uchetiv al damar
יום עברה היום ההוא, Yom evrah hayom hahu, a day of wrath,
אשר אין חליפות למו, asher ein chalifot lamo, there is no substitute
for him or exchange for him, so that means he does not
leave over a son who is seen as taking the place of
the father, ולא יראו אלהים, velo yiru Elohim, and they will not
see God. So רב יוחנן ורבי יהושע בן לוי. Rav Yochanan veRabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi. חד אמר Chad amar כגון שאינו מניח בן, kegon
sheino maniach ben, if the person doesn't leave over a son, that's
considered that he does not leave over an heir and somebody that
carry on the name and to be considered a continuation of the
person. וחד אמר Vechad amar כגון שאינו מניח תלמיד, kegon sheino maniach
talmid, somebody doesn't leave over a student, right? It's a spiritual heir.
As a teacher, right. So it's a spiritual heir, not necessarily not
not a biological heir.
תסתיים, Tistayeim, and that goes obviously plays in all those, you know,
tropes about like, you know, that a רב rav is like a
father and,
you know, השבת אבידה, hashavat aveidah, you return to the רב rav
first before the father and so on,
that ולימדתם את בניכם, velimadetem et beneichem, בניכם אלו תלמידיכם, beneichem elu
talmideichem, all those types of ideas that a student becomes like a
spiritual son. So רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan תסתיים, tistayeim, let's conclude רב
יוחנן דאמר תלמיד. Rav Yochanan da'amar talmid. רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan is
the one that says that it means a student, that that's what's
so important, דאמר רב יוחנן da'amar Rav Yochanan because רב יוחנן Rav
Yochanan would say דין גרמא דעשיראה ביר. dein garma de'asira'ah bir.
This is the bone of my tenth son. So this is the
story in ברכות Berachot that רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan would carry a
small bone. The רשב"ם Rashbam says it was a tooth because a
tooth doesn't cause טומאה tumah when it's not connected to the body.
He wouldn't want כהנים kohanim to become טמא. tamei. And when somebody
would, God forbid, lose a child, which would happen, you know, very
often in the ancient world, that you know there'd be infant death
and you know death of small children and so on because the
health wasn't as good and so on, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan to
console them would say like misery loves company, he would say like
you should know how much I've suffered similarly and this here, this
is the tooth of my tenth child who passed away, my tenth
son who passed away. So you know if we're learning ברכות, Berachot,
it's an interesting discussion about ניחום אבלים nichum aveilim and you know
and that, but here the point is that רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
did not leave any sons behind, had no sons to follow him,
right? All of his sons died. Certainly wasn't his fault, he gave
birth to ten of, I mean he sired ten of them, right?
But he did not leave but no son survived. So so clearly
if that's true, he would not be now he would not go
around teaching that somebody who did not leave a son, God is
filled with anger. Now why not? Because it makes so you would
think as it makes him look bad, right? But
the רשב"ם Rashbam says because then he would not be using this
to console somebody who lost a child if he was the same
person who taught that God is filled with anger. So it's not
just that it happened to him but that he would console
mourners with it. So תסתיים, tistayeim, that's a good proof, דאמר תלמיד.
da'amar talmid. רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan is the one who says that
the point is to leave over a spiritual heir. ומדרב יוחנן אמר
תלמיד, UmiDeRav Yochanan amar talmid, since רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan is the
one that says a student, רבי יהושע בן לוי אמר בן. Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi amar ben. רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi says that it's about leaving over a literally a child, a
biological son or not child, son. והא רבי יהושע בן לוי, Veha
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, but one minute but now that won't work
with what we know about רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Levi because רבי יהושע בן לוי לא אזל לבי טמיא, Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Levi la azal lebei tamya, he would not go to the
house a house of a house of mourners of mourning, he would
not go pay a שבעה shiva call, אלא לבי מא דשכיב בלא
בני.
ela
lebei ma deshachiv bela benei.
No, טמיא tamya is not טמיא tamya is not, טמיא tamya is
I think bones I think is the
Aramaic. But he would only visit a house a שבעה shiva house
if a person died without leaving over any sons. Okay, because that
he said would be like a real tragedy or maybe he felt
there were no sons there to be sitting as it's a little
ironic like who's sitting שבעה shiva there, the daughters, the wife. You
know, but then he would go because like maybe that's really what's
particularly poignant, you know, is that there are no sons who are
seen as the continuation to be sitting שבעה shiva and he said
that that was like a real tragedy. Why? דכתיב Dechetiv because it
says בכו בכה להולך, becho vecho leholech, go cry for the one
who goes. ואמר רב יהודה אמר רב Ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
להולך בלא בן זכר, leholech bela ben zachar, בלא בנים. bela banim.
Okay, with obviously it means those sons, male sons. So the one
that you really need to mourn for is somebody who died without
leaving over any sons behind because that man has no, you know,
seen as no obviously he could have daughters and so on but
in again in a patriarchal society is not seen as having anybody
that represents a continuation of himself.
So so now so because it seems like that if you see
this as a real tragedy and here's where it's very interesting, right?
It shifts from the idea of... God filled with anger to be
saying like that was a way of saying that this is like
a real tragedy, right? Because you'd say, wait, if you think it's
a tragedy, you wouldn't want to be saying that God's angry at
him. Angry suggests fault or whatever. But it seems, no, the point
of saying God is really angry is just another way of expressing
how terrible and tragic that situation is. Okay? So it's more like
God is like, you know, frustrated and disappointed than God is angry.
Like it's terrible. It's like it's somehow perverting what should be sort
of the natural sense of continuation, it's frustrating, you know, that sort
of that order. And so anyway, that's the real tragedy. So if
that's his approach, he clearly he would be the one to emphasize
how tragic it would be to leave to die without a son.
So אלא רבי Rebbe. יהושע Yehoshua, בן ben לוי הוא דאמר *Ella
Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi hu de'amar* wait minute. Did I get that
wrong?
Wait a minute. Oh. Has a
question.
No, no, no. Oh, so I think I was saying it the
wrong way. I'm sorry. So because he felt the tragedy of dying
without a son,
you wouldn't say that God's angry with him.
Oh, so the opposite of what I was saying. Okay, take it
all back. All right, too bad. I think I was trying to
make it nicer in my head, in my mind, but it wasn't.
All right, because, so forget that. Because he's framing it as a
tragedy, right, thank you, because it's not, it's not as nice as
I was saying. Because he's framing it as a tragedy, he wouldn't
say that God is,
what do you call it, that God is angry at the person.
אלא *Ella*, right, so not what I was saying. אלא רבי יהושע
בן לוי הוא דאמר תלמיד talmid, *Ella Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi hu
de'amar talmid*. Fine. רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* says
it means a student. And there God is angry because that may
be you're in your power to, you know, to raise to teach
students and so on. Also that, again, works a little better, at
least there could be some sense of fault or blame or whatever,
although again, you could teach many students and they all go off
the דרך *derech* or who knows what? But anyway, ומדרבי יהושע בן
לוי הוא
דאמר תלמיד *U'mid'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi hu de'amar talmid*.
What? רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* his 24... Right, רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*,
right, the Omer and tone. Anyway, but רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi* is the one who says God is angry at
the one who does not leave behind a student, and the one
who does not leave behind a son, that's a tragedy but not
that God is angry. ומדרבי יהושע בן לוי הוא דאמר תלמיד *U'mid'Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi hu de'amar talmid*, if he's the one that says
student, רבי יוחנן אמר בן *Rabbi Yochanan amar ben*. רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*'s the one that says that God is angry at the one
who doesn't leave over a son. So קשיא דרבי יוחנן אדרבי יוחנן
*Kashya de'Rabbi Yochanan a'de'Rabbi Yochanan*? So how, so first of all, he
himself didn't leave over a son, and how does he use this
as the way the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* says to console people if
he really thinks that God is angry? לא קשיא הא דידיה הא
דרביה *Lo kashya, ha didei ha d'rabbih*. It's his own teaching. He
himself actually holds like רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi*
that God is only angry at the one who doesn't leave behind
a student, okay, but he was saying it in the name of
his רבי *rebbi*. What was it?
I guess that would be funny too. Anyway, he's saying in the
name of his רבי *rebbi* that God is angry at the one
who doesn't have a son. It's still pretty ironic, right, that he's
going around... he doesn't even say in the name of his רבי
*rebbi* initially.
אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון Shimon. בן יוחי כל שאינו מניח
בן ליורשו הקדוש ברוך
הוא מלא עליו עברה *Amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai,
kol she'eino mani'ach ben l'yorsho, HaKadosh Baruch Hu malei alav evrah*. That's
how it's introduced. Oh, okay. All right, you're right. You're right.
That's בן ליורשו *ben l'yorsho*. You're right, so it's probably tying in
that statement of בן ליורשו *ben l'yorsho* to this statement of עברה
*evrah*, thank you. Okay, right, right, right, right, right. It's still funny
to be teaching in the name of your רבי *rebbi* something that
has very personal poignancy and sort of like saying, "My רבי *rebbi*
said that anybody who, whatever," and then it applies to him and
he lost ten sons or whatever. But anyway, but you're right. It's
tying in the first statement of כל שאינו מניח בן ליורשו *kol
she'eino mani'ach ben l'yorsho* with the statement of ולא יראו אלוהים *v'lo
yare'u Elohim*, and which makes sense, to tie those two רבי יוחנן
*Rabbi Yochanan*s together, but we're saying it's in the name of his
רבי *rebbi*. Yes, Rabbi Do...
how did you translate the last words of the first long line?
רבי יוחנן דין גארמי *Rabbi Yochanan, dein garmei*...
דין גארמי *Dein garmei*. This is the bone.
This is his bone of his tenth bier's son. Yes, of his
tenth son. Yes. All right. Okay. So, fine.
So and so that resolved it. So it was רבי יהושע בן
לוי *Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi* that says it's a tragedy to have
no sons and the sort of the more blame is assigned to
the one with that or with who didn't leave a תלמיד *talmid*.
And רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* agrees with רבי יהושע בן לוי *Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi*, but רבי שמעון Shimon בן יוחי *Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai* says God is angry at the one who leaves no son.
Later generations changed it a little bit and made it a תלמיד
*talmid*...
softened it maybe a little bit. Yeah. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says... Now, okay, now we're going a little more אגדתא
aggadata. *aggadata* before we get back to the halachic discussion. דרש רבי
פנחס Darash Rabbi Pinchas, בן חמא מה דכתיב *Darash Rabbi Pinchas ben
Chama, mah d'chtiv*, what's meant by the verse, והדד שמע במצרים *V'Hadad
shama b'Mitzrayim*, and Hadad heard in Egypt, כי שכב דוד עם אבותיו
*ki shakhav David im avotav*, that David lay down with his fathers,
וכי מת יואב שר הצבא *v'ki met Yoav sar hatzava*, and because
Yoav died. מפני מה בדוד נאמר בו שכיבה וביואב נאמר בו מיתה
*Mipnei mah b'David ne'emar bo shkhivah u'v'Yoav ne'emar bo mitah*? It's observing
that both of them died, why does one, does it use more
the euphemistic "he passed away, he lay down", and Yoav just says
"he died"? Okay, so דוד שהניח בן נאמר בו שכיבה *David she'heni'ach
ben ne'emar bo shkhivah*, maintaining the previous discussion, David left behind a
son, it says he lay down, it's not like he's dead, his
line isn't over, right, his name continues on. יואב שלא הניח בן
נאמר בו מיתה *Yoav shelo heni'ach ben ne'emar bo mitah*. Okay,
he died because in a certain sense that name and that family
died out. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says: יואב לא הניח בן *Yoav
lo heni'ach ben*? What do you mean he didn't leave a son?
והכתיב
*V'hachtiv*... יואב עובדיה בן יחיאל. Ovadyah ben Yechiel. A little bit of
funny עובדיה בן יחיאל. I thought it was בני יואב. bnei Yoav.
Anyway, אלא דוד שהניח בן כמותו נאמר בו שכיבה. ela David she'hiniach
ben kamoso ne'emar bo shkhiva. So now it's an interesting constellation of
the idea of son and תלמיד, right?
It's like it's not just a biological son, it's a biological son
that somehow
embodies your values and your virtues and so on. So it's also
like both a biological and a spiritual heir. So it's some combination
of the two.
ושיננתם לבניך. V'shinantam l'vanecha.
Right, I said that before. That was about תלמידים talmidim in general.
So that was the earlier debate. But here when we're saying בן
כמותו, ben kamoso, we're sort of bringing the two together.
Okay. אלא דוד שהניח בן כמותו נאמר בו שכיבה ela David she'hiniach
ben kamoso ne'emar bo shkhiva because then he only lay down, he
didn't really die, he was going to
sleep. His both his name and his values were continued, what he
stood for. יואב שלא הניח בן כמותו נאמר בו מיתה. Yoav shelo
hiniach ben kamoso ne'emar bo misa. There there was a death. Okay.
דרש רבי פנחס, I just have to say, you know, it's a
line Woody Allen said, says I don't want to, what's the line,
oh, I don't want to become immortal through my work, I want
to become immortal through not dying. So alright.
It
does so like the מדרש midrash of יעקב אבינו לא
מת.
Yaakov Avinu
lo met.
Right, that's true. That's the idea. That's a good point. That's the
יעקב אבינו לא מת, Yaakov Avinu lo met, right.
And Woody Allen, it's all very exactly.
Okay. So דרש רבי פנחס בר חמא, darash Rabbi Pinchas bar Chama,
since that was רבי פנחס בר חמא Rabbi Pinchas bar Chama we're
going to have a few more דרשות drashas of רבי פנחס בר
חמא. Rabbi Pinchas bar Chama. קשה עניות בתוך ביתו של אדם פעמים
יותר מחמשים מכות, Kashe niyus b'soch beiso shel adam p'amim yoser mikhamishim
mako, poverty in a person's house is more difficult, is harsher than
fifty
plagues, five times the plagues of Egypt. שנאמר, shene'emar, חנוני
חנוני אתם רעי כי יד אלוה נגעה בי. chanuni chanuni atem re'ai
ki yad elוה נגעה בי. This is איוב, Iyov, a lot of,
right, we have a lot of quotes of איוב Iyov in this
מסכת. masechet. You know, like give me a, treat me nicely, whatever
חן, chen, give me favor my, you my friends, because the hand
of God has touched upon me, has hit against me. וקאמרי ליה
חבריה, V'ka-amlei chaveirav, now why is that fifty plagues? It's like the
הגדה. Haggadah. אצבע אלוהים היא. Etzba elohim hi. And אצבע etzba is
ten מכות, mako, so five is fifty. ומעתה היד היא חמשים מכות.
U'mei-ata hayad hi khamishim mako. So okay, now so he says it's
like the fifty מכות. mako. And וקאמרי ליה חבריה v'ka-amlei chaveirav and
then his friends say to him, השמר אל תפן אל און כי
על זה בחרת מעוני. hishamer al tefen el aven ki al zeh
bacharta mei-oni. This is what you have chosen from poverty. Now what
does that mean? So the way the גמרא Gemara, is reading it
is at least whatever happened to you, your sons died, your daughters
died, you have all these, whatever, your body is filled with שחין,
shechin, yeah, with warts or whatever it is, your cattle died, but
it's better than being
poor. תוספות Tosafot says what do you mean, his cattle died? Fine,
his cattle died, but he still had a lot of money, cash
in the bank. That's the way תוספות Tosafot says. So somehow it
says at least it's better than being poor. So you see poverty
is worse than this which is equivalent to fifty plagues.
In all the קללות klalot coming up it doesn't say you'll be
poor.
That's true. דרש רבי פנחס בר חמא, darash Rabbi Pinchas bar Chama,
so fine. רבי פנחס בר חמא Rabbi Pinchas bar Chama also explained,
it's also interesting in the context of this פרק perek which is
all about inheritance, right? Anyway, כל שיש לו חולה בתוך ביתו ילך
אצל חכם ויבקש עליו רחמים. kol she-yesh lo choleh b'soch beiso yelech
eitzel chacham v'yivakesh alav rachamim.
If you have a sick person in your house which often in
the context means a sick person who's like possibly going to die,
go to a wise person and they will pray for you. What?
I know, so it's interesting. This is now the source of going
to a רבי. Okay, but here it's described not by a חסיד
chasid or by whatever but somebody just who's wise. And somebody if
you're wise somehow that means you have special access to God, which
is an interesting connection, right? Because normally you're right, the tradition recognizes
a difference like between חוני המעגל, Choni HaMe'agel, between people who are
righteous who are close to God as opposed to people who are
just wise. שנאמר, shene'emar, חמת מלך מלאכי מות, chamat melech malakhei mavet,
the anger of the king is, the king being God, are angels
of death. ואיש חכם יכפרנה. V'ish chacham yikhaprena.
And a wise man will atone for it or will cleanse it,
will be the one who can actually pray and intercede for God.
Okay, so that was a little אגדתא. Back to our discussion of
inheritance. זה כלל כל הקודם בנחלה יוצאי ירכו קודמים ואב קודם לכל
יוצאי ירכו. Zeh klal kol ha-kodem b'nachalah yotzei yerecho kodmim v'av kodem
l'khol yotzei yerecho.
So I want to just, we'll read this and then because the
גמרא Gemara. will now wrap up its discussions of the order and
then I'm going to go back to some of the questions that
were raised yesterday. Okay. So okay, so here we are, let's review
what we have.
Okay. So this guy dies, it goes first to his sons. Okay,
goes to his sons.
No sons, so that's number one, sons. No sons goes to his
daughter. But what we learned is... shares
that if, oops, that before it
goes to his daughter, it goes to any possible future generations, right?
Now, one of the questions that was asked, I might as well
answer it now, it's interesting. The question that was asked is, let's
say here you've got this generation, there was a son, he's dead,
and you have a daughter.
Is it going to go to the son's son, right? Son's daughter
even? Let's even make it that way. Oh, that son's daughter. I
got, I gotta say which generation. Anyway, what,
okay, anyway, okay, so
is it going to go here, right, to the original person's, is
it going to go to his granddaughter or will it go, let's
just make this, or his great-grandson, right? How much you continue to
preference the males once you keep on going down, down, down, down,
down? So, I looked at this in the, in the רמב"ם, Rambam,
in the, in the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, there was like no
discussion of it. I couldn't believe it because it's an obvious question
to ask, right?
Finally I found, when I got to the end of preparing today's
דף, daf, that in the long רשב"ם Rashbam at the end of
today's דף, daf, he summarizes all of the, all of the whole
order. He goes through it and he says, makes this comment. And
he says, he doesn't quote any גמרא, Gemara he just takes it
for granted that we're always going to preference sons. Like, that's the
rule. Actually, I shouldn't say that. He does quote a גמרא. Gemara
גמרא Gemara actually, I forgot, the גמרא Gemara says מקיש ירושה שניה
לירושה ראשונה. maki yerusha shniya liyerusha rishona. Remember the גמרא Gemara had
a case of בני אחות? bnei achot? Right, it had a case
where this guy dies and it goes to his nephew, בני אחות.
bnei achot. Do you remember that, here, whatever, they're brothers and sisters,
okay? It goes to, and it goes to his nephew. And the
גמרא Gemara says בני אחות ולא בנות אחות, bnei achot velo bnot
achot, right? It goes to his nephews not his nieces. So the
גמרא Gemara, says what do you mean it goes to his nephews
and not his nieces? If they're nieces they'd get it. He says
no, no, no, but the nephews get before the nieces. Okay? Remember
that גמרא Gemara basically? And it says that was מקיש
ירושה שניה, maki yerusha shniya, the next generation, right, לירושה ראשונה. liyerusha
rishona. So I actually had forgotten that גמרא, Gemara לירושה ראשונה. liyerusha
rishona. So the same way at this level boys get before girls,
men get before women, okay, when even if you have children that
are taking the place of a parent in that inheritance order, you're
still going to, the men are going to get before the women.
So that's why בני אחות ולא בנות אחות. bnei achot velo bnot
achot. It goes to the nephews before it goes to the nieces.
Okay? So therefore in this case, so that was exactly what people
were asking yesterday, and therefore in this case, okay, the same way
it'll go to this son's descendants, and if he has any living
descendants before it goes to his sister, then if this, well whatever,
this man's sister, it'll go to any of his descendants before it
goes to his sister. As it passes down, it'll, if he has
a boy and a girl, it'll go to any of those boy's
descendants before it goes to the girl. So you're it's always going
to go, you know, so again, it might wind up that it
goes to this
great-great-great-great-great-great-granddaughter before it goes to her and before it goes to a
lot of women along the way, right? But the basic rule is
that it'll always go to the boy before the girl and always
to the boy's descendants before it goes to the girl, even if
those descendants are girls. Alright?
But it's only if there's no boys in that other line.
Right? Right, exactly. Because if you have to choose at any level
between a boy or a girl, you go to the boy. And
then if that boy doesn't isn't alive, you go down even if
it's going to mean going to a girl. But at that next
level, if there's a boy and a girl, you always go towards
the boy.
Wait, but, but if at that level there's a boy and a
girl, the boy dies but has a son. Yes. It goes to
his son?
Yes. Yeah, yeah, that's what I'm saying. You always will go, you
identify who the heir is at this level and then you look
for any descendants before you move over to the next. So here
we've, if we've identified the boy would be the heir over the
girl, right, you look for any descendants, any, well first any boys
and then, right, yeah, exactly, exactly, yeah. And the again, to remind
you also, the interesting thing is, is that is that, is that
you could have this daughter gets nothing, this son gets together with
this great-great-great-great-great-granddaughter because she's taking the place of, you know, because this
means you're entitled to an inheritance.
And now we've got, on the left, it's another son. Oh, you're
saying it's three kids now.
He has three kids, okay. So we first identify who's entitled to
an inheritance, and then we find out who is there to take
the, who is there as a direct descendant that can take that
person's place. Even though it means that now you'll have some great-great-great-great-granddaughter
together with a son that gets, and the daughter herself is cut
out.
That רשב"ם Rashbam. is really clear. He says כך סדר נחלה. kach
seder nachala. Right? Okay.
Alright.
So the business we have to take care of that daughter's just
part of this. What? The בית דין, Beis Din, if that daughter's
not married, they have to take care of her.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So she has, she's provided by the estate before
she goes to get married. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this: בעי רמי בר חמא. Ba'ei Rami bar Chama. Okay, everybody,
בעי רמי בר חמא. Ba'ei Rami bar Chama. אבי האב ואחי האב.
Avi ha'av ve'achei ha'av. כגון, Kegon, אברהם וישמעאל בנכסי עשו. Avraham veYishmael
benichsei Eisav. Ha!
Bet you weren't expecting that! We were all talking about Reuven and
Shimon, but we don't want to talk about—if we're going to talk
about somebody dead, we'd rather it be that Eisav be the one
who's dead. So, Rabbi Dov, don't distract
people. So you have Avraham, okay, Avraham. Who
were Avraham's sons, everybody?
Who was—well, Yishmael's the בכור, bechor, actually. Yishmael and Yitzchak, okay,
and Yitzchak's sons were—well, Eisav also was the בכור. bechor. Okay. All
right, so, all right, everybody you all passed Bible 101. So, okay,
he wanted to
know. Okay. כגון, Kegon, אברהם וישמעאל, Avraham veYishmael, these, they're alive, and
Eisav dies, and Yitzchak is dead. Okay? So who's going to get
Eisav's inheritance? All right, so, and Yaakov would be dead for the
purposes of this. All right? So first you would go to his
kids. He doesn't have kids. Then you would go to his father.
His father is dead. Better have been—remember that?
Yeah, that Abraham outlived all the grandchildren. Yeah, exactly.
Real case.
Then he goes to his father's dead. Then it goes to his
brother. Brother is dead. Okay, so now the question is: Do you
go to his grandfather or do you go to his uncle? Right?
אחי האב Achei ha'av or the father of the father? So, Rami
bar Chama, אבי האב, avi ha'av, אבי האב, avi ha'av, right, ואחי
האב, ve'achei ha'av, ואחי האב. ve'achei ha'av. כגון, Kegon, אברהם וישמעאל בנכסי
עשו, Avraham veYishmael benichsei Eisav, איזה מהן קודם? eizeh meihen kodem? Which
one comes first? So אמר רבא: amar Rava: תא שמע, Ta shma,
האב קודם לכל יוצאי ירכו. ha'av kodem lechol yotzei yereicho. So he
says, well, the father comes before all of his descendants. So that
means that the father would have to come
before the uncle Yishmael. What?
Avraham comes before Yishmael, right.
Hold on, let me just... I do understand that.
Hold on, wait a minute.
But Yishmael can't inherit before his father does.
Right, right, right, right. Hold on. Right.
I don't know what the question
is.
Hold on.
Okay, right, fine. Okay, yeah, right, there isn't a question. Okay, fine.
All right, I just have to double check something. Right, so it's
like we said before, because what we said before is, is that
before—you know,
the reason Yishmael gets is that Yishmael would get through Avraham. So
you—remember the basic rule here is, I'm sorry, the basic rule here
is, right, in
any particular person, there's really only two things you have to know:
בן and then בת bat and then אב. av. And everything else
follows from that. Okay, so first you go to a son, no
son you go to a daughter. No daughter you go to a
father. No father, so then you go to this rule again. So
then you go to the father's, to the father's children, which is
this man's brother, brothers and sisters. Right. No brothers and sisters, then
you go up again to the next father and then you go
like that. So you're constantly going like that. Okay. That's basically how
it works. So that's האב קודם לכל יוצאי ירכו. ha'av kodem lechol
yotzei yereicho. So Eisav dies, it would go to his children. No
children, it goes to Yitzchak. Yitzchak's not around, goes to Yaakov. Yaakov
isn't around, so then it goes up, so then it's like it
was Yitzchak's property. And if Yitzchak died and had no kids here,
it would go to Avraham. Avraham isn't around, then it goes to
Yishmael. So האב קודם לכל יוצאי ירכו. ha'av kodem lechol yotzei yereicho.
So what's the question? So the גמרא Gemara says...
yeah, before you continue, yeah. Did you just fit that into those
words? Like, in other words, האב קודם לכל יוצאי ירכו, ha'av kodem
lechol yotzei yereicho, לכל יוצאי ירכו של מי? lechol yotzei yereicho shel
mi? Like, I get what you're describing, but I don't see how
it fits in the words.
Why not? Avraham comes before Yishmael, and
any father and his descendants. Descendants.
But it doesn't work. The children inherit before the father.
No, they don't.
They don't? Before you go back up a generation to the grandfather,
children inherit.
Which children? If Eisav dies, Yaakov doesn't inherit before Yitzchak. Eisav's children
inherit, so that's what the גמרא's Gemara's going to say, that יוצאי
ירכו yotzei yereicho only means the first generation of the
father. Right. So the גמרא Gemara's says: ורמי בר חמא אגב חורפיה
לא עיין בה. Verami bar Chama agav churpeih lo ayin bah. Rami
bar Chama because he was so sharp, he was starting about speculative
questions and he didn't realize that it was already basically answered from
the משנה, Mishnah, that האב קודם... ha'av kodem... קודם לכל יוצאי ירכו.
kodem lechol Yotzei Yerecho. But now the גמרא Gemara's going to get
to Rabbi דב Dov's question, which is it's not really true. It's
לכל יוצאי ירכו lechol Yotzei Yerecho because that would mean that if
עשו Esav were to die, יצחק Yitzchak would get before עשו Esav's
kids. And then kids would never inherit if we really treat לכל
יוצאי ירכו lechol Yotzei Yerecho literally. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
going to next get to.
Okay, okay, משנה Mishnah says לכל יוצאי ירכו, lechol Yotzei Yerecho, יוצאי
ירכו, Yotzei Yerecho, right?
Well, let's see. Okay, so בעי רמי בר חמא, ba'ei Rami Bar
Chama, so here's the question of רמי בר חמא. Rami Bar Chama.
אבי האב ואחיו, Avi ha'av ve'achiv, כגון kegon אברהם ויעקב Avraham veYaakov
בנכסי עשו. benichsei Esav. Okay, so now we want to know, forget
ישמעאל, Yishmael, okay,
so who to give it to? יעקב Yaakov or אברהם? Avraham? Now
יעקב Yaakov's alive. Based on the principle I told you, you go
to his sons, no sons, you go to יצחק, Yitzchak, יצחק Yitzchak
isn't alive, it goes down to יעקב. Yaakov. Okay, but if it
says, but here's the question that Rabbi דב Dov asked, if we
say האב קודם לכל יוצאי ירכו, ha'av kodem lechol Yotzei Yerecho,
so maybe we obviously know יוצאי ירכו Yotzei Yerecho does not mean
direct descendants of the dead, right? Direct descendants of the dead obviously
would come first. But once we're not dealing with direct descendants of
the deceased, maybe אברהם Avraham should come before any of his descendants.
Once we've excluded the obvious case of the direct descendants of the
dead. So in this case, maybe it should go to אברהם Avraham
and not
יעקב. Yaakov. Okay, so that's לכל יוצאי ירכו. lechol Yotzei Yerecho. So
כגון אברהם ויעקב בנכסי עשו איזה מהם קודם. kegon Avraham veYaakov benichsei
Esav eizeh mehem kodem. אמר רבא amar Rava תא שמע ta shma
אב קודם לכל יוצאי ירכו. av kodem lechol Yotzei Yerecho. Okay, what
does that prove? Doesn't really prove it. It's, I mean, that's what's
questioning what that word means. But what רבא Rava is saying is,
that means that יצחק Yitzchak inherited. And conceptually, even though he's dead,
and once יצחק Yitzchak inherited and then יצחק Yitzchak isn't around, it's
obviously going to go to יעקב. Yaakov. But it doesn't really, how
do you know, whatever. The problem is he's not addressing the meaning
of the words לכל יוצאי ירכו, lechol Yotzei Yerecho, which is what
the גמרא Gemara's going to say. ורמי בר חמא veRami Bar Chama
יוצאי ירכו שלו ולא יוצאי ירכו של בנו. Yotzei Yerecho shelo velo
Yotzei Yerecho shel beno. Oh, I'm
sorry, I'm sorry, I apologize. רבא Rava first actually thought that the
answer was what, I got confused because of the א aleph of
הלכה. halacha. But רבא Rava actually gave an answer that is not
the הלכה. halacha. רבא Rava actually gave the answer that it is
אברהם. Avraham. Like that makes sense why he's saying. The question is,
so עשו Esav dies, who should get it? So רבא Rava says,
what do you mean who should get it? והאב קודם לכל יוצאי
ירכו. veha'av kodem lechol Yotzei Yerecho. He's reading that phrase literally. אברהם
Avraham gets it before יעקב. Yaakov. All right, now he, again, I
don't think we're saying he would get it before עשו Esav's kids.
But bracketing out the direct descendants, once you're somewhere else in the
chart, אברהם Avraham is going to get it before יעקב, Yaakov, right?
The granddad. ורמי בר חמא veRami Bar Chama and רמי בר חמא
Rami Bar Chama says, wasn't so sure. יוצאי ירכו שלו ולא יוצאי
ירכו של בנו. Yotzei Yerecho shelo velo Yotzei Yerecho shel beno. No,
יוצאי ירכו Yotzei Yerecho means only his first generation descendants. He would
not come before his son's descendant. Okay, which is basically, and that's
the way we actually rule, like רמי בר חמא, Rami Bar Chama,
not like רבא. Rava. But it's funny that the גמרא Gemara did
not have that clear because that phrase לכל יוצאי ירכו lechol Yotzei
Yerecho sounds that אברהם Avraham would come before יעקב. Yaakov. But רמי
בר חמא Rami Bar Chama says, no, no, no, it just means
that at the first generation you don't go to a brother before
you go to a father. Meaning if עשו Esav dies, you don't
go to יעקב Yaakov before you go to יצחק. Yitzchak. Okay, he
comes before his first generation of kids. But he doesn't come before
his second generation of kids. Okay, הכי נמי מסתברא. hachi nami mistavra.
You know what? That reading makes more sense. דתני de-tani זה הכלל
כל הקודם בנחלה יוצאי ירכו קודמין. ze haklal kol hakodem benachalah Yotzei
Yerecho kodmin. Anybody who comes first, his descendants come first. So okay,
ואילו איתא ליצחק, ve'ilu iteih le-Yitzchak, had יצחק Yitzchak stood around, יצחק
קודם. Yitzchak kodem. So if יצחק Yitzchak was alive, he would have
gotten from עשו. Esav. So now he's not alive. So what's the
rule? If somebody isn't alive, who do you give it to? Kids.
Right? Remember this whole chart here, if the son isn't alive, you
find a descendant. So the גמרא saying fine, let's look at this.
עשו, Esav, he has no children, none of them. So it goes
to יצחק. Yitzchak. יצחק Yitzchak isn't alive. What's the rule when somebody
isn't alive? You find a living descendant. So you go to יעקב.
Yaakov. So יעקב Yaakov is taking יצחק Yitzchak's place and you follow
that order before you go to a different place in the chart.
Right? So that's the logic here and that's important because at the
end it's really, they collapse to some simple rules. Okay, the reason
you don't go to אברהם Avraham and instead you go to יעקב
Yaakov is because if somebody isn't alive you look for direct descendant
to take their place before you move to a different place on
the chart. Okay, so the person himself dies, you look for direct
descendants, right? And then that was this whole chart. If there's a
boy and a girl it goes to the boy. If the boy
is dead you look for a direct descendant of the boy. You
look for direct descendant follow, you know, always following the males as
opposed to the females at any particular level. If If there's no
direct descendant, you move in the chart. So where do you move?
You move to the father. That's all you have to know.
Son, daughter, father. And that if the person isn't around, you look
for their descendants. So the father isn't around, before you go anywhere
else in the chart, you look for their descendants and you give
it to יעקב. Yaakov. If there's no descendants of יצחק Yitzchak then
you move in the chart and you go to אברהם.
Avraham. If יעקב Yaakov in your chart, if יעקב Yaakov would have
been יעקובה, Yaakova, a sister, yeah, she would have gotten before אברהם?
Avraham? Yes, exactly.
So there's a
deep there's a deep idea here that's like יבום. Yibum. In other
words, a person can replace another person in a way for some
type of continuity.
Right, and the whole דרשה drasha that we learned that you go
for direct descendants of ואינה לו vainah lo is a similar דרשה
drasha we make for יבום. Yibum. Exactly, that any descendant boy or
girl, right, this
idea of continuity and name and place that's underlying all of it.
Correct, correct. Okay, דאי לא יזיב יצחק יצחק קודם הכא נמי דאי
לא יזיב יצחק יעקב קודם
שמע מינה. de'ee lo yeziv Yitzchak, Yitzchak kodem, hacha nami de'ee lo
yeziv Yitzchak Yaakov kodem, shema mina. So you see that's the point,
that before you're going to go up to אברהם, Avraham, even though
the principle says לכל יוצאי ירכו, le'chol yotzei yirecho, you cannot treat
that too literally. It basically means to his first descendants, because we
follow the more dominant rule which is before you move in the
chart you look for direct descendants. Okay, so there's a couple of
rules. Basically all you have to know is this. Okay, I mean
if you want to you could say these are the three people
in the chart and the order, בן בת אב. Ben, Bat, Av.
Okay, that's point number one. Point number two is before you shift
over to a daughter or to a father or whatever, before you
shift, you know, look for direct descendants.
Look for direct descendants, and the descendants and I think there was
only one more rule that I wanted, was that the only rule?
Before going back to the previous generation,
no, before you go down... whatever, no, before you move from a
boy to a girl or from a girl to a father, before
you move anywhere on the chart, look for direct descendants of that
person. Right, and I guess, yeah, the other thing is that even
in, you know, even in the direct descendants, okay, boys come before
girls. Boys before girls. You know, and those three rules basically cover
the whole thing.
And number one, בן בת אב. Ben, Bat, Av.
Yeah, but that's even if you go... I know. That's just ירושה
שניה לירושה ראשונה. yerushah shniyah le-yerushah rishonah.
That's it. That collapses all of them. I mean it's pretty interesting
that you can collapse it to those rules. I do want to
say by the way that the fact that there was like no
commentaries on שלחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch on this, and you know, you
would imagine like this is not so obvious, right? I mean all
of this whatever and it was not anyway. To me is an
indication, I would have to research it more, but I just imagine
like I think it was probably rare that they actually
implemented this, probably because of will, that they used wills. But still,
people would have died without wills. So you know, I don't know
exactly how they would have handled it. I do want to say
one other thing though that's important, or two other things that I
found in trying to research some of this and then I found
it was in the רשב"ם. Rashbam But in the course of researching
that, I found two interesting things. Number one is the רמ"א Rama
says, I'm surprised nobody here asked this question, Michael, you should have
asked this question, which is... I'm teasing you. Which is, let's say
somebody dies and you don't know who the father is and they
leave over no children. Who do you give the property to? So
we... so the most obvious thing is you would say give it
to the mother. Right? I mean if there's no father, you don't
know, or the father's a non-Jew. There is no halachic father. Alright?
Nowadays we could say artificial insemination, okay, whatever, or no, you know,
you don't know or non-Jew, what do you do with it? Logically
you would say give to the mother. But remember we said the
mother never gets going up, right? So the... so rather than say
you give it to the mother, the רמ"א Rama says it's like
when a גר ger dies, the property becomes הפקר. hefker. So that's
I think pretty amazing, right? That you would make the property would
be considered הפקר hefker rather than give to the person's biological mother.
So that's like one really interesting thing I found out. There was
another interesting question which is a story about a guy that had
a whole fight with his mother and then the... and then he
basically the town made him swear, like take an oath and whatever
and say "I am completely removing myself from my mother's inheritance and
I have no portion in my mother's inheritance." Okay? And he did
a קנין kinyan and a שבועה, shvuah, who knows whatever he did.
I don't know if he did a שבועה. shvuah. Anyway, then his
mother died and then he said "I want my mother's inheritance."
So basically the פוסקים poskim said look, this goes back to this
issue that it's not just דיני ממונות. dinei mamonot. I said before
I discussed this in the context of דינא דמלכותא דינא. dina de-malchuta
dina. You can't... it's not like a decision between two parties that
you can remove yourself, you know, and say "I'm waiving my rights"
or whatever. It happens automatically. So the same way we wouldn't go
by the secular law because it's not a decision between parties that's
shaped by secular law, it's a חקת משפט. chukat mishpat. You cannot
just remove yourself. You can make as many types of קנינים kinyanim
that you are waiving your rights and removing yourself, you're still going
to inherit. However, they said in this case... Since it was part
of the way since it was the way the community was punishing
this guy and fining this guy, it would be binding for a
different reason, but as a general rule, you cannot remove yourself from
the line of inheritance.
Yes, passing by
the law, right? Passing by to disinherit?
The way you disinherit somebody is by writing a will and giving
all your property to somebody else. Right. Okay.
If there was no will, he couldn't, so it would go, right.
Everybody could say you're getting nothing and he could say and the
tit-for-tat I'm getting nothing and then it would happen. Okay? All right,
so let's look at the let's start the next משנה. Mishnah. בנות
צלפחד נטלו ג' חלקים בנחלה. Bnot Tzelofchad natlu gimel chalakim benachala. חלק
אביהן שהיה עם יוצאי מצרים וחלקו עם אחיו בנכסי חפר ושהיה בכור
נוטל שני חלקים.
Chelek avihen shehaya im
yotzei mitzrayim vechelko im achav benichsei chefer veshehaya bechor notel shnei chalakim.
So we are back now to my צלפחד Tzelofchad picture. Okay,
so here is, oh, those are the two sons. Okay, this is
חפר, Chefer, this is צלפחד. Tzelofchad. Don't know why they have now
rings around them, but okay.
צלפחד Tzelofchad is dead and then it goes to his daughters. All
right, fine.
So the גמרא is going to learn out from פסוקים pesukim that
both
חפר Chefer himself had a portion in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
the brothers had portions in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. And when חפר
Chefer died, so צלפחד Tzelofchad got his father's portion, his portion in
his father's portion plus the portion he was entitled to himself. Why
did they all have portions in the land of ישראל? Yisrael? So
the first key principle is
ליוצאי מצרים
נחלקה הארץ, leyotzei mitzrayim nechlekah ha'aretz, which basically means they're all going
in, right? It's the end of במדבר. Bamidbar. It says לאלה תחלק
הארץ בנחלה. le'eileh techalek ha'aretz benachala. So לאלה le'eileh you would think
it actually means to the generation that's about to enter in. Okay,
but according to this approach, you looked at all of the people
that left מצרים, Mitzrayim, you maybe first of all I express my
they probably first figured out which tribe gets what, right? And then
within each tribe, okay, שבט דן Shevet Dan gets this area. Let's
take a list of all the names of the people left מצרים.
Mitzrayim. There were 100,000 men or whatever left מצרים Mitzrayim or whatever
it would be. We're going to give each one one-100,000th, we'll divide
it up into little squares. Not for דן, Dan, I'm talking about
within a particular tribe because you first have to decide the נחלה
nachala of the tribe. Okay, I mean, whatever, that's a little bit
debatable. And then they get it, and then if they're alive when
they enter in, which they won't be unless they were under twenty,
okay, if they were alive when they enter in they'll hold on
to that portion. If they died from the time you're doing this
retroactively because you're doing the division in the time of יהושע, but
you're retroactively pretending as if those that left מצרים Mitzrayim got ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. It's a very profound idea, right? They were promised
to enter in, they didn't enter in, but conceptually they inherited ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Anyway, they got ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and in
their portion and now they're not around, so you divide it amongst
their heirs. But the power of doing it this way of יוצאי
מצרים yotzei mitzrayim is let's say no, not just more, let's say
you had these two people that left Egypt, okay, ראובן Reuven and
שמעון. All right? And then they left Egypt with no kids. In
the מדבר, midbar, שמעון had ten kids and ראובן Reuven had one.
Okay. So now when you divide and these are the guys that
go into the land of ישראל, Yisrael, right? This guy gets equal
to all these ten combined because you're looking back at what it
was when they left Egypt. So that's principle number one. So the
assertion is all of these people were יוצאי מצרים. yotzei mitzrayim. חפר
Chefer and his well, I don't know about צלפחד's Tzelofchad brothers, but
anyway חפר Chefer and צלפחד Tzelofchad both left Egypt. So they both
got one portion in the
land. Then צלפחד Tzelofchad died and so that portion, so that's anyway
that's one portion, okay, and that portion is going to pass on
to his daughters. חפר Chefer died, I mean before they entered into
the land, and this portion got divided amongst the brothers. How much
did each one get? Well, because we're going to assert that צלפחד
Tzelofchad was a בכור. bechor. So you divide this into four into
four, okay, I mean
I'm making it up that there are three brothers,
and he gets those two portions. Okay. So that's what it says
צלפחד Tzelofchad got three portions. Let's read that again. בנות צלפחד נטלו
ג' חלקים בנחלה. Bnot Tzelofchad natlu gimel chalakim benachala. חלק אביהם שהיה
עם יוצאי מצרים Chelek avihem shehaya im yotzei mitzrayim because he left
Egypt he got one portion. וחלקו עם אחיו בנכסי חפר. vechelko im
achav benichsei chefer.
Now these חלקים chalakim are not as big as this חלק, chelek,
right? Right? You see that these חלקים chalakim are it's a חלק
chelek of חפר, Chefer, but חפר Chefer and צלפחד's Tzelofchad חלק. chelek.
So anyway and his ושהיה בכור נוטל שני חלקים veshehaya bechor notel
shnei chalakim and because he was a בכור bechor he got two.
So now the רשב"ם says that what this is teaching us other
than an historical interest, something of historical interest, is number one, the
division went to the people who left Egypt. מצרים, Mitzrayim, not the
people who went into ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, was defined by that.
Number two, although we know if somebody isn't around, his descendants get,
you might have said, well, that would only be if there were
nobody else at that generation. You might think give it to the
brothers, and maybe boys or girls nobody's going to get down here.
You'd rather give it only to this generation rather than to some
lower. No, that the lower generations replace, even if they're women, they
replace, and that's חידוש chidush number two, that they actually are going
to get what he got from חפר. Chefer. חידוש Chidush number three
is that he gets פי שנים, pishnayim, and this is a חידוש,
chidush, because he's already dead when חפר Chefer dies. So when somebody
dies, and his firstborn son is dead, does the firstborn get a
double portion that passes on to his heirs? Like you could understand
saying like, I don't think so, does that make sense? Like, you
know, logically if your first, but no, the הלכה halacha is that
since his daughters are taking his place, and if he were alive
he would get a double portion, even when he's dead he gets
a double portion, okay? So that is so now that's the flip
of the general principle is אין הבכור נוטל בראוי כבמוחזק, ein habechor
notel barauy k’bamuchzak, you might remember that. So which is, let's say
the opposite happened. Let's say חפר Chefer died, and he got his
whatever double portion from חפר. Chefer. Then חפר Chefer's father died, okay?
Then it would have,
had חפר Chefer's father died first, חפר Chefer would have gotten it,
and then he would have given him a double portion, right, of
his father's. But if חפר Chefer's dead, he's not going to get
a double portion from up here. So it only is what חפר
Chefer has in his possession when חפר Chefer dies. That's the principle
that it has to be מוחזק muchzak in חפר Chefer's possession. Okay,
but he doesn't have to be around to receive it. If חפר
Chefer has that, he gets it, and if he's not around, his
kids get it. You had a question, Dinah?
Well, yeah, just now I'm confused when you said it like that,
that the kids are going to inherit even if they're girls, right?
Right.
Before that, so
then I'm confused about when we did that long generation of descendants
before where we said the boys get preference even if they're in
a lower generation. Right. Isn't it just like passing down and then
like, okay, this guy three generations later should get it but he's
dead and he has a daughter and a grandson? Right.
No, so what I kept on saying there was was that you
prefer the boys at the same level. Meaning, so if they're, you
don't go down to look for more boys. If at this level,
right, there's a boy and a girl, you give it to the
boy. If the boy is dead, you give it to the girl
and you don't look for replacement, grandson doesn't, isn't preferable. But if
at a given level, right, no, wait, wait, wait, wait, no, no,
no, no, no, no, no, maybe I
misstated it. Hold on. Let's see. The guy dies and he's got
a son and a daughter.
So
if the right, if the son is dead, you're right, you do
keep on going down. Okay, hold on, hold on. You do keep
on
going down a generation if the son is dead. Oh, but no,
your question was if the daughter here is dead, you would not
prefer her son
over her sister.
Right. You would not do that. Okay? You're always looking
so down generation is to replace someone. Never gets more than the
person they're replacing, if you think about it that way. You know,
whether you're if you're a boy down here, you don't get you
you function as as a woman at this stage. You know what
I mean? You never get more you more than the generation that
you are replacing. You get as much as. Here the girls and
they're getting together with their brothers. I mean, that's a good way
of thinking, right? Just think of them as the replacement for that,
not for themselves. So because they're replacing their father, they get together
with their brothers and they get a double portion and and they're
girls. Okay, but the flip is, if this boy is down here
and his mother is dead, he's not going to trump his aunt.
He'll get together with his aunt, but he's representing his mother. Okay,
so you so it's never when you're going down a generation, it's
who you're representing, not who you are. Is that pretty is that
clear?
Yeah. Okay, but if his if the if it wasn't his mother,
it was his father, if
it was his father, then he would get before his aunt. Even
if it was a daughter, she would get before her aunt if
she's replacing her father. For the same logic, you are the person
you're replacing, you're taking the role of the person you're replacing. All
right, I want to say one more thing just about this, is
which is part of the חידוש chidush here though is because of
this principle that a בכור bechor only gets in something that's
מוחזק, muchzak, question is what do you mean it's מוחזק? muchzak? It's
ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. They left מצרים. Mitzrayim. They never had it
in their possession. So the fact that you're going to have the
rules of... A בכור, bechor, he's going to get double, is another
important assertion that this משנה Mishnah is making, which is ארץ ישראל
מוחזקת היא, Eretz Yisrael muchzeket hi, okay? You know, you know, so
it's already considered, not only do we think the people left מצרים
Mitzrayim were deserving to inherit, but it's considered that they already inherited,
and they were already מוחזק muchzak in the land of Israel, and
therefore the laws of בכור bechor apply and he gets a double
portion. All right.